<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe censure vpon the Puritane pamphlet entituled, (humble motyves, for association to maintayne religion established.) Reprooving of it so many vntruthes, as there be leaues in the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852123</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852123</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17430</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16612)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17430)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1128:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe censure vpon the Puritane pamphlet entituled, (humble motyves, for association to maintayne religion established.) Reprooving of it so many vntruthes, as there be leaues in the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>75 [i.e. 91], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English Secret Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed M. DI. III. [sic] [1603]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anonymous response to:  "Humble motives for association to maintaine religion established" (STC 3518), the first part of which is signed: T. Diggs.</note>
                  <note>Roman numeral date is misprinted on title page.</note>
                  <note>The words "humble .. established" on title page are enclosed within parentheses.</note>
                  <note>Page 91 is misnumbered.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and press from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humble motives for association to maintaine religion established.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17430:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17430:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE CENSVRE V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PON THE PVRITANE <hi>PAMPHLET:</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g> ENTITVLED, (HVMBLE MOTYVES, for aſſociation to maintayne Religion eſtabliſhed.) <hi>REPROOVING IT OF SO MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Vntruthes, as there be leaues in the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PRINTED M.DI.III.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:17430:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17430:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE CEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVRE VPON THE <hi>PVRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TANE PAMPHLET: ENTITV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> (Humble Motyues for Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation to maintaine Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on eſtabliſhed.)</head>
            <head type="sub">REPROOVING IT OF SO MANY Vntruthes, as there be leaues in the ſame.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE I. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT my firſt entrance of account, may giue to all equal and indifferent Readers, ſome proportion to make conie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, how large and great a number of wicked and malitious Vntruthes, are contayned in ſo little and ſhorte a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe: As I will beginne my reckoning at
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17430:3"/>the Title, and beginning it ſelfe of this <hi>Aſſociation:</hi> So for euery worde which it conteyneth, being only ſix (beſides the particles, &amp; adiections of our language) I will aſsigne a ſeuerall falſehood. And the firſt ſix Vntruthes, for the firſt ſix wordes. For although the common de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of Philoſophers teacheth vs, that <hi>Verety and falſity, truth and falſchoode, conſiſt not in particular dictions, and firſt apprehenſion, but in Compoſition or Diuiſion, and in Iudgment:</hi> Yet becauſe that firſt Title is ſo copious, that it may eaſely bee reſolued into ſixe ſeuerall Compoſitions, Propoſitions, and Iudgments, which it vertually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyneth: that is, that <hi>they be Motyues; that the Motyues be Humble: that they be for Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: that the aſſociation is to maintayne Religion: that the purpoſe of the Pamphletor is Religion: that their Religion is establſhed:</hi> All which aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they be plainly intended in that glorious Poſition, and ſix in number, I challenge them to bee ſo many ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and impious Vntruthes and forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>And concerning the greate humilitie either of Puritanes in generall, or of this
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17430:3"/>
                  <hi>Aſſociator</hi> in particuler, affirmed in the firſt worde <hi>(Humble)</hi> I appeale for ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to the Iudicials of al trials; Popes, Councels, generall, prouinciall, confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, not confirmed, all holy Fathers, and Doctors of the Church of God, all Arguments diuine and humane, natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and miraculous, which their proud and arrogant ſpirit in the baſeſt Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane hath condemned: I craue cenſure of all Emperours, Kings, Princes, their lawes, decrees, and Parlaments, which euery of them as repugnant to their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, haue cenſured and reiected: whether this is humility the foundation of piety, becauſe hee pleadeth it in this firſt place: or pride and arrogancie the mother of all Irreligion, rebellion to God and man, and other monſtrous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences which they haue brought into the worlde, by that moſt ambitious, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, and blaſphemous doctrine: <hi>that euery Puritane is directed, and infallibly aſsiſted of the ſpirit, and may controle</hi> at their pleaſure, all Popes, Princes, Councels, Parlaments, and Conſiſtories of al times and places. Which hath cauſed the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17430:4"/>Puritanes of England, ſo often by their <hi>Admonitions, Challenges, Pamphlets, Inuectiues, Iabels, and rayling</hi> ſlaunders, to reprehend Queene, Councell, Parlament, Clergy, and whatſoeuer is of eſtimation in this kingdome. And is the motyue which at this preſent mooueth this humble <hi>Aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciator,</hi> to direct them all, and preſume, that his only deuiſes are worthy to ſway the Scepter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE II. VNTRVTH, CONCER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſecond worde: <hi>Motyues.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MOtyues</hi> are ſo tearmed <hi>a mouendo, of moouing:</hi> and <hi>motyues of the mind</hi> take their denominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe they mooue and perſwade the vnderſtanding, and will of man to yeeld conſent vnto, and aſſect ſuch thinges as they convince, the one to allowe, and the other to embrace: for as in naturall and corporall motion, from whence this tearme is deriued, the leuity &amp; grauity of bodies are the cauſe which mooue them, the firſt to aſcend, and the ſecond to a lower Center. So
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17430:4"/>in the motions of the reaſonable powers of mans ſoule, that reaſon and argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which conquereth humane vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, to giue conſent to that ſentence which it conuinceth, and that approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued bonity and goodneſſe which win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the will to affect the good which is propoſed, are iuſtely named, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyues which mooue thoſe reaſonable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties. And as in ordinary and naturall affaires, ordinary and naturall reaſons are ſufficient, and allowed for motyues: So in ſupernaturall and diuine thinges exceeding the naturall wit and capacity of humane Iudgement, ſupernaturall and miraculous Arguments are produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. For which cauſe Catholickes the knowne patrons and deſendors of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity againſt all, both externall, and internall aduerſaries, produce not only the authorities of ſo many and muinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble teſtimonies of holy Scriptures tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes, ſentences of ſo many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, and generally approoued Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and aſſemblies of the beſt learned Doctors and Profeſſors of the worlde,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17430:5"/>togither with the abſurdities of all other Profeſsions: But to confirme diuine bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſines with the infallible reaſons of God, and to mooue men to embrace that, to which by naturall reaſon they can ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſcend or aſſent; They produce ſo many and manifeſt miraculous operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, works, and wonders; ſo many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall predictions, and fore-tellinges of future contingent euents, to eſtabliſh thoſe miſteries wrought of God to that purpoſe; which no created power of it ſelſe to any end, or by the power and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance God can bring to effect to rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any errour or ſuperſtitious falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode.</p>
               <p>Nowe let vs examine the <hi>Motyues</hi> of this Moouer by theſe proportions, and trie whether they bee worthy to bee <hi>the firſt mooueable</hi> or no. If we conſider what it is, which he laboureth to remooue, it is that Catholicke and vniuerſall Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Chriſt, which hath mooued the whole worlde to approoue it by ſuch ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable motyues as haue conuerted it. They which ſhould be mooued to this, and to bee drawne onely by his motion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17430:5"/>are our prudent and gratious Princeſſe, her wiſe and Honourable Councell, the reſte of the Nobility, the Proteſtant Clergy, &amp; whatſoeuer is reputed great, and of the higheſt iudgment in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hee which would mooue them, is endued with that Puritane ſpirit, which is in continuall moouing, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer findeth his place of reſt, and vvho for his diſſolute and deformed motion, ſhrowdeth himſelfe vnder the title of an erring Planet, not daring to diſeloſe his name. He citeth not one example or authority for his purpoſe. Thoſe which he alleaſdgeth for Motyues, be none at all; as her Maieſtie her ſelfe, Councell, Nobles, Burgeſſes, Biſhoppes, and the whole conſent of Commons, which are to be mooued by his Inſtince, had giuen ſentence in open Parlament immediatly before. And the meanes which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth, either in the ſame, or more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible manner, had bene practiſed many yeares togither, as will be euident here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, and no man but ſuch a ſpirituall fellowe can beignorant: And yet they coulde not preuaile to that motion.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17430:6"/>Therefore no Motyues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE III. VNTRVTH, ABOVT THE third worde, <hi>(for Aſſociation.)</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE name <hi>Aſſociation</hi> is deduced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Socius,</hi> a <hi>fellowe</hi> or <hi>Companion,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a noune of <hi>Action</hi> and doing, muſt needes fignifie to make fellowes, and companions. In which, and al ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binations there muſt of neceſsity bee as well a kinde of equality (otherwiſe no fellowſhip but a ſubordination) as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſimilitude, likeneſſe, and agreement, as is euident in all coniunctious. For if two or more differing thinges bee ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and vnited together, this agreeing matter muſt of neceſſitye be ſuch, that the thinges to be reconciled doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent therein. Thoſe which bee of one kinred agree in bloude; The domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calles of one familye in cohabitation. Thoſe which bee of the ſame Religion (which is the <hi>Aſsociators</hi> caſe) to haue the ſame Sacriſice, Prieſthoode, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and other Rites and Ceremonies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17430:6"/>belonging vnto Reuerence. If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the quallitie which is required to <hi>Aſsociation,</hi> I truſt it wil not be an humble Motiue, for ſuch people to be fellowes with Prynces, and theyr owne Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne: Some wright that the Earles of England be termed <hi>Comites,</hi> becauſe by curteſie of our Kinges they haue both beene ſo named, and in ſome ſorte ſo vſed; But that Title was neuer giuen to inferiour Nobles. Then it maye not be yeelded to ſuch vnable ſpirits: except (which is the marke they ſhoote at, and which priuatlie they beleeue) all things muſt be in communitie, and no Superious Spirituall or Temporall may be allowed. How the ſecond cauſe of vnion betweene the proteſtants of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland and the Puritanes thereof in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, can bee deuiſed, differing in 32. pointes as their admonition witneſſeth, I cannot conceaue. For this Puritane Motor maketh no ſubmiſion that they wil refor me to the Parlament doctrine. Then either there can bee no <hi>Aſſociation</hi> or elſe the Queene and Parlament muſt reuoke their lawes and onely maintaine
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17430:7"/>Puritaniſme, which is the ſecond pricke of their leuell as appeareth by his owne vvordes, of which I will ſpeake more heareafter</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE IIII. VNTRVTH. IN THE fourth worde <hi>to maintayne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE worde <hi>To maintaine</hi> as it ſuppo ſeth the beinge of the thing to bee maintained, ſoe it muſt yeelde ſufficient cauſes of preſeruation and maintenance to the ſame. Towchinge the firſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers doe call <hi>Duration</hi> a continuance of beeing becauſe at leaſt in prioritie of nature it ſuppoſeth the exiſtence and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing of that, whereof it is a duration or continuance. In the ſeconde Reſpect that whiche maintaineth an other, muſt be more Noble and Potent, then that which is maintayned and ſtronger then thoſe aſſailing enemies which ſtriue to ouerthrow it. The Maſter maintayneth his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the Soueraigne his ſubiect, &amp; in naturall cauſes, the more general and powerable doth maintayne &amp; preſerue
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17430:7"/>the weaker. The Sun among the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets is called an vniuerſall cauſe, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde ir preſerueth and giueth mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to theſe inferiour thinges. And all creatures are maintayned by GOD, without whoſe maintenance and aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, all thinges would be annihilate. In the firſt ſence, <hi>Puritaniſme</hi> and <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> with the Profeſſors thereof, cannot giue duration to Religion. For that which this Pamphletor laboureth to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh, was neither by any kinde of <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority,</hi> or <hi>Simultity,</hi> which I can finde now is authorized in England; but of this I will make challenge in the worde <hi>Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh.</hi> In the other meaning to ſpeake of maintenance, I thinke all Proteſtants are very farre from giuing credit, that Puritanes ſeeke to maintaine their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And that they are deſtroyers and not maintayners thereof,<note place="margin">Parliam. 5. Parlia. 23. Eli. Synod. Lond 1562 l. art.</note> hath bin often concluded in the higheſt Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lament, the booke of Articles it ſelfe, by the whole Proteſtants Clergy of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, with a double Subſcription. And touching any motyue that may mooue this high conceit of their proceedinges,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17430:8"/>that diuinity which I haue learned tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth me this for moſt founde and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine doctrine, that as there is nothing ſo vndoutedly true, as the articles of true Religion, which is taught and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed of God: which as he is infinitely wiſe and good, ſo he can neither be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued in himſelfe, or giue cauſe of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror vnto others, ſo that which maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth this trueth and certaintye, muſt needes be moſt true and infallible, (eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye thinge beeing maintayned by ſuch meanes by which it conſiſteth.) Then the lying ſpirit of Puritanes by which euery baſeſt fellowe is to preſcribe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to the vninerſall worlde, and no doctrine can be maintained without that mans allowance, cannot be a mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance but deſtruction to true Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: as to giue a ſhorte example in a briefe difcourſe,<note place="margin">Epip. Haer. Aug. Haer. Bern. later. Catal. Haer. Vlenb. l. 22. Cauſ. Rain. Cal. turaiſ.</note> there haue beene by morall iudgement, 700. ſectes of Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, which haue pleaded this kinde of maintenance. Therefore it is oddes 699. to one, that Puritanes will deſtroy and not maintaine Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17430:8"/>
               <head>THE V. VNTRVTH, IN THE fift worde: <hi>(Religion.)</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>REligion</hi> is that due worſhip, which man oweth and is to render to God his Creator, and chiefe omnipotent Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor; for ſo many fauours wherewith he hath enriched him. And which man is to receaue hereafter by his inſinite &amp; ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recompenſible bounty. This worſhip, as it is the Reuerence of God, in whoſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable will &amp; pleaſure it is, by what homage and offices hee will be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; ſo the inſtitution thereof, muſte needes proceede from him, and Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of it to man. In which regard, it is an impoſsibilitie that any Article or Queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of duty by that incrrable pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſo ordeyned, and propoſed, ſhoulde either be vntrue, variable, vnconſtanr, or vncertaine, as this (ſo by themſelues called) <hi>Religion</hi> of Puritanes, which ſo daily altereth,<note place="margin">Aug. Her. Epiph. Her. Bern. Later. Catal. Her. Caſp. vlen. l. 22. cauſ. &amp;c.</note> as the wanering ſpirit of euery Profeſſor thereof, floweth and eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vp and downe. And 700. to one as is recited, by actuall experience it is vntrue, ſo many ſeuerall and oppoſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17430:9"/>ſects by that ſoundation grounding ſo many diuers and contrary profeſsions in diuine reuereuce. Of which by neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequence al but one muſt needs be falſe, and by no probability that can be true.</p>
               <p>Secondly ſeeing this holy worſhippe is that obligation and bond whereby (as the name it ſelfe, Religion, teacheth vs) man is bounde and religed vnto God, for ſo many giſtes and graces where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee is adorned, and aduanced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue other creatures: the office and exe cution of this reuerence muſt bee ſuch that it religeth and binde all faculties and powers of man to perſorm that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Then if wee compare puritane pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which catholicke worſhipp it ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth no ſemblance of <hi>Religion.</hi> for all ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of that holy Reuerence be affirm a tiue and teaching one point of deuotion or other, as the affirmation of ſo many ſacred miſteries of prieſthoode, Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſice, Inherent grace, ſeauen Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, with their ſupernaturall effects, prayer, Inuocation of Saints, prayer for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and other meanes to keepe man
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17430:9"/>ſtill bounde and religed vnto GOD. And if by frailty or otherwiſe he chance to breake thoſe bandes of Religation, Penance, Contrition, griefe and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctin of minde and body, to relige and binde him againe. If we reſemble this Puritane doctrine to the proteſtancie of England, it likewiſe is a Negation of all Religion, denying ſuch affirmatiue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles as they had left.<note place="margin">Admonit: Parl. 1.2. I. W. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Admonit.</note> For nowe the Parlament muſt haue no ſentence, the Communion booke is fooleries, and damnable, al the Courts, and Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Proteſtants, are become dennes of theeues and ſerpents. The names of Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Arch-deanes, Deanes, and ſuch, be Dyabolicall. No ſigne of the Croſſe, or memory of mans Redemption may be vſed:<note place="margin">Aſsoc pag. 39.</note> and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer religeth a man to God, muſt not be remembred vnder their curſe, for ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. If we put theſe people into bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with the idolatrous Gentiles, Turkes, Iewes, and Brachmans, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident by al writers, that although thoſe Infidels doe erre in true Religion, yet they maintayne forged Prieſthoods, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17430:10"/>and other tokens of Reuerence, to keepe in ſeare of a diuine Maieſty: all which thinges be wanting in this Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, hauing no one poſitiue or affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue opinion, concerning worſhippe. And ſo for Religion and binding of men to God, haue brought in a plaine priuation of thoſe duties, irreligion, and a freedome to all liberty and vndutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, both to God and man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE VI. VNTRVTH, IN THE ſixt worde: <hi>(eſtabliſhed.)</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is euident by the whole diſcourſe of this Religious <hi>Aſſociator,</hi> (and ſo hee rearmeth himſelfe in diuers places) that he is a Puritane, and laboureth to ſettle that ſame profeſsion as he bewrayeth in plaine tearmes.<note place="margin">Pag. 19</note> And yet who knoweth not, but Puritanes be condemned, at the leaſt (as before) in 32. queſtions, by that Religion which is ſetled in England,<note place="margin">Admonit Purit. Com. B Parl. 5. et 13. Elizab.</note> as their owne Admonition, the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion booke, and Parlaments themſelues are witneſſe againſt them. Therefore
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17430:10"/>this Innouator ſeeketh not to aſſociate to maintayne any Religion ſetled, but to ſettle his own vnſetled ſect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE VII. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>THE ſeauenth foule and flattering Vntruth, is two leaues longe; as though Puritanes were the moſt loyall, louing, and obedient ſubiects, which her Majeſtie hath: and in reſpect of them, neither Councell, Nobility, Biſhops, or any other, were dutifully carefull of her preſeruation. But Sr, becauſe you pretend you ſelfe ſo dutifull a Subiect to our Soueraigue, and regardfull of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to the Engliſh Proteſtant Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and that Religion which they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, you will giue me licence to vtter in a fewe wordes, the true allegeance and loue, which your reformed <hi>Seignorie</hi> and elderſhip beareth vnto them: For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this affection be knowne to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in your Society, you will not bee worthy to be admitted to ſuch exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fauour with our Queene and her
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:17430:11"/>Biſhops to whome you write. Then I will condemne you by your owne ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, to be vndutifull to her Maieſty our Queeene, moſte malitious to her Clergy, and deuoted Aduerſaries to their Religion; for whoſe maintenance you counterfeite deſire of <hi>Aſſoctations.</hi> And to exemplifie, what forreigne Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is ſo gratious in your eies, as that of <hi>Geneua,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonit. parl. in fin. Repl. Admon. Parl. tract. 20.</note> and other Churches there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts, which you call (for that reaſon) reſormed? your Admonition to the Parlament approoueth the <hi>Presbitery</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the French Puritanes ſo farre, that you propoſe them for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of imitation to England: your owne writings I hope you will not deny: And if you forſake <hi>Caluin,</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and deareſt friends, you are diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited for euer. Then to begin with them firſt, which I named laſt, let the Reader iudge, vvhether our Soueraigne, her Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, with the reſt of the Parlament Miniſtery, and their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſo contrary vnto Puritanes, liue in ſecurity, &amp; be honoured by this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Concerning Princes which be not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:17430:11"/>of <hi>Caluins</hi> purity, he vſeth theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Caluin. in Da. c. 6. v. 22.25. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſpoile themſelues of all authority, yea they are vnworthy to bee accounted in the number of men, and therefore we muſt rather ſpit vpon their heades, then obey them.</hi> And touching the Engliſh Communion booke, which is the rule of Parlament Religion, hee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it <hi>fooleries.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Stat. 1. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz. Surn. of hol. diſc. Beza epiſt. ded. nou. teſt. an. 1564. et e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcop. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor.</note> 
                  <hi>Beza</hi> euen in his Epiſtle to <hi>her Maieſtie</hi> of England, defendeth Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt Princes of a different Religion, and honoureth ſuch as bee ſlaine in ſuch quarrels, with the glory of Martyrs. And in his Epiſtle to a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Biſhop of England, condemneth the exerciſe of their Religion. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches of France holde the ſame ſentence, both concerning King, and worſhip in their 39. Article.<note place="margin">Congreg. artic. 39. Articul. Puri. Scon</note> Two of the chiefeſt Articles of the Scottiſh Puritanes be theſe. 1. <hi>Biſhops, and Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, haue no authority, their very names and titles, be Antichriſtian and Diabolicall:</hi> 2. <hi>It is hereſie for any Prince, to call himſelfe heade of the Church. But he may be excommunicate and depoſed of his miniſters.</hi> And to come to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Puritanes, and the <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> of your <hi>Elderſhip</hi> and reformed <hi>Scignorie,</hi> the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17430:12"/>Patron thereof T. C. is knowne to be an ancient and mortall enemy to the preſent Arch-biſhoppe of Canterbury, and is farre from allowing the Titles, names, dignities, and authority of him, or any Biſhop, Deane, high Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onor, or other by her Maieſties procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that as the ſame Arch-biſhoppe hath gathered to my handes,<note place="margin">T. C. in repl. to the anſ. of the Admonit. I. whitgift prefat. to the anſ. to the Reply of T. C. T. C. in Repl. in fin Confeſ. c. 18. T. C. repl. pag. 5. T. C. pag. 144.</note> he wil not allowe him the dignity of a Doctor, but Ironice and ſcoffingly (after your man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) calleth him <hi>M. Doctor</hi> 370. times at the leaſt, in one litle book. And telleth vs that the equality of Miniſters, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirmed by the ſentence of the Puritanes of <hi>Heluctia, Tygurine, Berne, Geneua, Polmia, Hungary,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> with others. And although you to ſlatter the Proteſtant Arch-biſhops, and Biſhops of England, woulde bring your diſagreement from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toceremonies, yet he deſendeth, that the doctrine of the Engliſh Proteſtants is ſuch, that Puritanes are bound to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, with loſſe of as many liues, as they haue haires on their heades. And for reuerence and duty to our Soueraigne, denounceth by his Euangelicall preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17430:12"/>againſt all Proteſtant Princes, which will not be Puritanes, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their <hi>Presbitery,</hi> that (to vſe his own wordes) <hi>They muſt ſubmit their Scepters, and throwe downe their Crownes before the Church</hi> (of their Elderſhip) <hi>and licke the dust of their feete.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The higheſt cathedrated ſentence of your Admonition, written in all your names rayleth at the Proteſtants, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming your contentions to be but Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. But I will alleadge the wordes of that holy worke, both for your confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in this, and all other your wicked practiſes in this <hi>Aſsociation:</hi> Theſe they be. <hi>Lordy Lordes, Arch-biſhops, Biſhoppes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prefat. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Parl. Admonit. tra. 2.3. &amp;c:</note> 
                  <hi>Suffraganes, Deanes, Doctors, Arch-deacons, Chauncellors, and the reſt of that prowde genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whoſe Kingdome muſt downe: Titles, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, and offices of Metrapolitane, Arch-biſhop, Lordes grace, Lordſhippe, Suffrragane, Deane, Arch-deacon, were deniſed by Antichriſt, and are plainely in Chriſts worde forbidden, and are vtterly with ſpeede to be remooued.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prefat. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monit. ſupp.</note> 
                  <hi>But in a few wordes to ſay what we meane: either must wee haue a right miniſterte of God, and a right gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Church, according to the Scriptures
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17430:13"/>ſet vp (both which we lacke) or elſe there can bee no right Religion, nor yet for contempt thereof, can Gods plagues be from vs any while deſerred. Wee in England, are ſo farre from hauing a Churche rightly reformed, according to the preſcript of Gods word, that as yet we are not come to the outward face of the ſame.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonit. tract 10. Tract, 11.</note> 
                  <hi>In the booke of Common prayer, a great number of thinges contrary to the worde of God are conteyned. Except they yeeld, not onely Gods inſtice ſhall be powred forth, but alſo Gods Church in this Realme, ſhall neuer bee builded. The way therefore to auoide theſe inconueniences, and to reforme theſe deformities is this: to remooue Aduouſons, Patronages, Impropriations, &amp; Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops authority. You muſt plucke downe without hope of reſtitution, the Court of Faculties, remooue Homilies, Articles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Con. Lon. anno 1562. Parl 5 Eli. Booke of ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticles &amp;c. Tract. 17. admonit.</note> (this is the Book where the ſumme of Engliſhe Proteſtant do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is allowed) <hi>Iniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> (the Queenes ſpirituall laws) <hi>a preſcript order of ſcruice</hi> (the Communion booke) <hi>take away the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the loytering, the pompe, the idleneſſe, and liuings of Biſhops, &amp;c. In ſteede of Chauncellors, Arch-deacons, Officials, Commiſſaries, Proctors, Doctors,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonit. tract. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Sumners, Church-wardens, and ſuch like; you haue to place in euery congregation, a lawfull and godly Seignorie. The Lord Biſhops,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17430:13"/>their Suffraganes, Arch-deacons, Chauncellors, Officials, Proctors, Doctors, Sumners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tract. 18. ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>and ſuch rauening Rablers take vpon them, which is most horrible, the rule of Gods Church. The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops Court, is the filthy Quauemire and poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Plaſhe of all the abbominations, that doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the whole Realme. Neither is the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie betweene them and vs, as they would beare the worlde in hand, as for a Cap, a Typpet,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Addit. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monit. Admonit. Parl. Tract. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>or a Surpleſſe, but for greater matters, concerning a true Miniſtery, and Regiment of the Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the worde. To theſe three ioyntly, that is, the Miniſters, Seniors, &amp; Deacons, is the whole Regiment of the Church to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted.</hi> Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be the wordes of that holy Puritane ſentence. And that it may be manifeſt, what their loyalty and loue is to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, her Biſhops, and their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings both in temporall and Religious affaires; making no exception at all,<note place="margin">Tract. 23</note> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Queene, councell, Biſhoppe, or whatſoeuer (except poore ignoraunt ſoules) they beſtowe their holy bleſsing vpon all, which will not allowe of their <hi>Admonition,</hi> and holy <hi>Elderſhippe,</hi> in theſe tearmes following: <hi>God confound them, that his peace may be vpon Iſraell, &amp; his ſaumg health
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17430:14"/>vpon this Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Now let the Reader iudge whether theſe men ſeeke <hi>Aſsociations</hi> to preſerue her <hi>Maieſty,</hi> her State, and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or no, or whether they intende ſo great loue and duety to the Proteſtant Biſhops, as is gloſed in this Pamphlet, or that no kinde of Subiect is ſo carefull as they, to preſerue the honour and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et of our Kingdome.</p>
               <p>Let vs now ſee whether this be true or no. Philoſophers and Diuines teach, that to loue is <hi>velle alicui bonum,</hi> to wiſhe good to the beloued, then by how much more good is wiſhed, by ſo much the loue is greater: &amp; leſſe, when leſſe good is deſired, and where no good but euil is wiſhed,<note place="margin">Pa. 1 lin. 4.</note> it is hatred. This Pamphletor himſelfe acknowledgeth in the fourth line of his worke, that 3. things in due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty are to be <hi>exhibited</hi> by the <hi>Subiects</hi> to the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> that is, <hi>Honor, Obedience,</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</hi> Then who hath performed theſe duties to our <hi>Soueraigne?</hi> none but Puti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine call honour is temporal or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, the firſt is moſt dutifully yeelded of all, both Proteſtants and Catholicks; of ſpirituall honour the Catholicks make
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17430:14"/>diſtinction and are diſliked chiefly for that opinion. But this Puritane friend abſolutely denyeth the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth doubtfully of the firſt. As for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual honor, the caſe is euident in al their aſſertions. And towching the terrene honour of a <hi>Princeſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Goodm. li. demonſtr. Regim. mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>her.</note> was not <hi>Goodman</hi> in the time of <hi>Q. Mary</hi> a Geneuean Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, and yet he tearmed the temporall regency of a woman <hi>Monſtroſum Regimen, A Monſtrous Regiment.</hi> And this was the doctrine of his conſorts, and practiſes of their Diſciples.<note place="margin">Stowe hiſt. in Q. Mary Groft. &amp;c.</note> For who were they which laboured ſo much to depoſe not onely that Catholicke Queene but our preſent <hi>Soueraigne.</hi> No man will ſay that they were Catholickes, therfore I ſay and prooue that they were Geneuean Puritanes (our Engliſh Parlament Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancie then not being eſtabliſhed or knowne, but diuers yeares after in theſe dayes.)<note place="margin">Iacob Rex Scot. in li. Regin. ad fil.</note> Are not the Miniſters of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Puritanes? then aske the King himſelf (if the booke of Regiment pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in his name did come from him) how full of honour, obedience, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence this people is in that country, he
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17430:15"/>complaineth of them aboue all others in deſect of theſe duties.<note place="margin">Petr. frar. or. cont. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctar Staphil. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. fixe to. 2. Mon. teſt. tr. ordin. Burg in remonſt. ſup. edict. Reg Gal. pare. 2. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. Reg. &amp; Relig.</note> Were not <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin, Beza, Spiphanius Othomanus,</hi> the <hi>Swizer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; French <hi>Hugonites</hi> Puritaines? yes, and be ſo accounted in England. And yet what Councels &amp; Conſiſtories did they keepe to depoſe Kings &amp; Princes? what baſe and tyranicall Vſurpers did they erect? what lawfull Magiſtrate in Fraunce was not deputed by them to death. Who haue more turbulently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haued them ſelues in theſe times then this deceitfull and lying Sect. What Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, Admonitions, threatnings &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendges hath this people made againſte Queene, and all kinde of magiſtrates, eſpeciallie the Proteſtant Biſhops and miniſterie, with whom they would now in words be aſsociated? Demande an hundred ſooleries of Martin Marpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, this Writer and his companions. This is the honor and obedience, they vſe, and defence whiche I feare they would exerciſe, if it came to tryall. Let them examine Catholiks by theyr owne Rule of rendring dutie, of honor, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and defence: They were Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17430:15"/>which firſt crowned her with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, they were Catholiks which obeyed her, when they were powerable to be diſobedient. Then by all preſumption Catholickes will euer defend her. And I truſt with our prudent Princeſſe and Councell, the malitious inuentions &amp; falſehoods of Puritans to aduance them ſelues, nor the lewde ſlander of any A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtata, to excuſe his impietye will be admitted, againſt the conſciences of ſo many Religious Prieſts and Ieſuites, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouned in al parts of the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> world, proteſting (euen with daylie dangers, and death it ſelfe) theyr Innocencie in theſe affaires.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE VIII. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>THIS Pamphletor affirmeth that the eſtate of our Soueraigne is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſlye impeached with the Perill of her Perſon, by the indeuour of Papiſts, to bring in the Superiority &amp; Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of a Forraigne Prelat &amp;c. I meruaile where this man learned his conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17430:16"/>Is the Superioritie and Supremacy of Pope, or any forraigne Prelate, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſed in ſpirituall and eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call cauſes, dangerous to the Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall eſtate of any Ciuill Ruler, or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate? or perilous to their Perſon? Be not thoſe Regiments diuers and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, euen in the iudgement of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes themſelues? then the one is not perilous to the other. How many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares, were they thus deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded among the Iſraelites without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. or perill one to another? That Nation came to moſte calamities,<note place="margin">Li. 1. Mach Li. 2. Mach. Ioſephlib. antiq. &amp; bell. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. Cronol. Bellon Tox to. 1.2. bill. turrie. Petr. Maſſ. lib 1.2.3. hiſt. indie:</note> when theſe Regiments were vnited togither, about the time of the Machabees, and after: In the Turkiſhe Regiment the Caliphes Rule in Religious cauſes, and yet without perill to the Imperiall State. Among the Indian Pagans the Brach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ouer-rule their Princes in like ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, yet without preiudice to their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, or Temporall dignities. Among the ancient Gentiles, the Fle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mens and Archfle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mens had that charge: &amp; yet no Temporall Regency endangered. And now in Italy, Spame, France, Polonia,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17430:16"/>the Empire, and ſo manye Catholicke Countries, the Romaine Iuriſdiction ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in ſpirituall affaires: And yet what State of theſe countries? What Perſon of thoſe Princes is by that in peril? And in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d when that Superiority reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it ſo many hundred yeares, and in the daies of almoſt 200.<note place="margin">Fox tom. 1. Mon in Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal. Reg. Stowe hiſt.</note> Kinges of this Nation, which of their eſtates or perſons vvas endangered by that Regiment? then it is not the doctrine of Catholickes in this point, any plot or practiſe by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which palyeth at hazard with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Princes, or draweth kingdomes to ruine: But it is the preſumptuous, &amp; factious opinions of Puritanes, vvhoſe priuat ſpirit in euery meane and vnlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man, doth not only condemne the ſentence of Queene and Parlament, and her Superiority, by that title in ſpirituall buſines, but may by their Profeſsion, &amp; doth by open Pamphlets, &amp; Inuectiues, controle all Princes, and Magiſtrates, both in Ecclefiaſticall and Temporall cauſes: and diſpoſe of Kingdomes, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis, and Cities, at their high will and pleaſure as they did at Geneua, Collin,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17430:17"/>in France, and other places as I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE IX. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>BVt if we will beleeue this Puritane, her Mareſties Perſon ſhall ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in peril, except his coufaile be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted for her deliuery: by which ſhee ſhal be enfranchiſed from ſuch dangers. His preſernatine and <hi>Antidote</hi> (to vſe his phraſe) followeth in theſe words. <hi>It would be enacted, that all Gentlemen, Magiſtrates, and Poſſeſsioners within this Realme, ſhall take the oath of Aſſmiation, for the defence and perpetua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of Religion now publickely profeſſed within this Realme. And the oath of Supremacy be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mſtred with like addition, to all men generally within this Realine, from the age of ſixteene yeares vpwardes, twice euery yeare, by the Mayors, and Couernours of Cities, Townes, and Corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and by Stewards and other Officers in Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and Lordſhippes in their Cuntreis, and their Leetes, and Law-daies. And if they refuſe to enter into ſuch league or oath. that eucry ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſhall be holden and reputed as ſuſpected, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17430:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhall be thereby diſabled to beare any office, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in Common wealth, and ſhall alſo be bound to his good behauiour, ſequeſtred from all his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onour and weapons, and (if hee bee poſſeſſed of lands within this Realme) ſhall yearly pay vnto your Maieflie, the fourth part thereof. &amp;c.</hi> This is the ſentence of this Solon: In vvhich, how many vntruthes and fooleries there be, it is not an eaſie account. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I deale in liberality with this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, I will put the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> togither in one. Firſt then I conclude by this high Authority, that Puritanes bee moſt wicked, lying, and dangerous members in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and moſte worthy by their owne iudgment, to incurre theſe penalties, which they practiſe againſt Catholickes. For if this inuention were put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, Catholickes ſhoulde become ſo impious (as Puritanes be) to make no account of oathes. This ſtratagemme coulde take no effecte, but the Queene would be more endangered both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the perils pretended more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, and the offendors coulde not be diſtinguiſhed, friends coulde not bee decyphered from enemies. But by this
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17430:18"/>mans confeſsion, all Puritanes be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt aduerſaries to her Maieſtie in this matter; for they both deny the Religion now publickly profeſſed in the Realme, as alſo her Maieſties Supremacy in moſt vncharitable tearmes. Then when Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes (as this man aſſureth) will take theſe oathes, both concerning the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſhed in England, and her ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Eccleſiaſtical power, which they ſo much condemne, they be condemned to be the moſt impious, irreligious, and diſloyall people, vtterly vnworthy any office, credit, or confidence in common wealth: but by their owne lawe to bee bounde to theſe diſablements, penalties, and payments, which they inuent for Catholickes, whoſe fidelities, wordes, &amp; oathes, may be admitted for ſecurity of the greateſt perill, as theſe men acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by this Inuention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE X. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>BVT to manifeſt farther the folly &amp; falſchood of this dreame &amp; deuice.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17430:18"/>If any coulde be ſo mad to imagine that ſo wiſe a <hi>Princeſſe, Councell, Nobility,</hi> Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Clergy, and Commons (for he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth that his law may be preſently ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) would immediatly after the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of a Parlament, wherein theſe toyes were reiected, ſummon the whole kingdome againe to pleaſe ſuch people. Yet his intent againſt Catholicks would not be obtayned. I will not examine the particulers of his fooleries therein, but experience ſhall pleade againſt him, for either the ſame or more grieuous haue beene enacted, and are daily executed againſt vs; &amp; yet he maketh theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of perilles by encreaſe of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes within this kingdome. For firſt concerning his oathes of the Reltgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now eſtabliſhed, and her Maieſties Supremacy, are they not tendered to all Magiſtrates at their admittance? The firſt Parlament it ſelfe only excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the Nobles of this Realme,<note place="margin">Parl. 1. Eliz &amp; 5. Eliz.</note> to whom this man likewiſe ſeemeth to allowe that exemption. And How often haue ſuch oathes and interrogatories beene mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred to the Catholickes of this Nation,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17430:19"/>Gentlemen, and other Poſſeſsioners, &amp; not Poſſeſsioners, whome this lawe-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker includeth not?<note place="margin">Stat. 1. Eliz. c. 1.</note> the Satute of Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy giueth the ſame authority for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the oath of that Superiority in as ample manner as he preſcribeth; only he aduiſeth it to bee taken twiſe in the yeare, which limitation imployeth no other vſe or end, but to make men diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in ſwearing, &amp; forſwearing as theſe Puritanes be; for who wil hope for truth in him, vvhich is accuſtomed to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare, which by all lawes be reiected for witneſſes. And this great Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an himſelf, calleth al Parlament perſons (which applauded not their deuiſes) Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes: and yet moſt of them had taken the oathes which hee preſcribeth. But harken vnto his penalties. The denyers of theſe oathes, ſhall only be diſabled to beare office, bounde to the good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, ſequeſtred from their armour &amp; weapous,<note place="margin">Pag. 23. Stat. 1. &amp; 5. Eliz.</note> and pay yearely, the fourth part of their landes to the Queene. How ridiculous is this man? Is it not <hi>Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mre</hi> to deny that oath by lawe already e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacted? how many Catholickes know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17430:19"/>this man to be in office in our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? are not Catholickes bounde both to the good behauiour, and depriued of their Armour and weapons? And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the laſt puniſhment, to pay the fourth part of their lands; they only poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe a third part, and her Maieſty, or rather wicked perſecutors enioy the reſt and no rent at all is anſwered vnto her, by ſuch Tenants for thoſe landes. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Puritane abuſed her, and his propheſie is falſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XI. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>FOR Reuerence to her Maieſtie, I paſſe ouer the holy bleſſings, which he beſtoweth vpon the Romane See, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Prieſts, <hi>grana Benedicta, Agnus Dei,</hi> &amp; hallowed thinges from thence. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this man is ſo methodicall in his diuiſions, for he which teacheth ſo wiſe a <hi>Princeſſe,</hi> and Councell, both in diuine, ciuill, and martiall affaires, muſt needes be an Abſolute; Then I will giue him due in all his excellencies. Theſe be the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17430:20"/>wordes of his firſt diuiſion. <hi>The power &amp; ſtrength of any people or multitude, is to bee aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by one of theſe foure waies.</hi> 1. <hi>By addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or number.</hi> 2. <hi>By ſupplie of Neceſſaries.</hi> 3. <hi>By aduantage of place.</hi> 4. <hi>By order of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, as I am no computing writer, ſo I haue beſtowed little labour in them which handle ſuch employments: And I thinke your ſelfe to bee as wiſe as the Orotor of Greece, which ſo perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie entreated ſuch things before <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> that greateſt Captaine in the worlde. But I thinke if you had well committed to memory, the warres and battailes of <hi>Abraham, Gedeon, Sampſon, Ioſue, Dauid,</hi> and others recorded in Seriptures, wherein you and yours bee ſo inſpired: or with ordinarily qualited Gentlemen of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, taken but a ſuperficiall Muſter of the warres of <hi>Alexander</hi> with <hi>Darius.</hi> Of the Chriſtians, againſt the Moores in <hi>Spayne.</hi> The Spanyards againſt the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidels in the Indies. Or <hi>Henry</hi> the fifte and other Engliſh Kinges in France. Or beene a little acquainted with <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> which you cite in the beginning
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17430:20"/>of the firſt page of your Motyues, you would haue beene mooued to adde o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther members to your diuiſion, gyuing it as an inſtruction to ſo greate a <hi>Princeſſe.</hi> But Souldiers ſhall giue you this Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion. And I will in this point onely call to your remembrance, that you diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>played your Banner to farre, for a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of ſmall experience, and which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer kept Centinell before, may eaſelie diſcouer, that according to your skill, you labour to poſſeſſe your parte of all thoſe meanes, by which you thinke <hi>the power and ſtrength of any people, or multitude,</hi> (I vſe your owne tearmes) <hi>is to be augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> Your firſt fortification is <hi>by addition or number:</hi> of this you would eaſely bee owners, if you might teach Queene and Councell, and haue ſuch ſtratagems in vſe, which none but your holy fraterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty doth allowe. Your ſecond embataile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is rayſed <hi>by ſupplic of Neceſſaries,</hi> of which you woulde alſo be Maſters, if all Armour and weapons were brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Armouries. Of the third, which is <hi>aduantage of place,</hi> you would haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage enough, if none but of your al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17430:21"/>lowance might be admitted to place of Magiſtracie, or be placed in any office or place of defence. As for the fourth and laſt <hi>order of gouerument,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 41. inſr.</note> you triumph al ready, that moſt men of action and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution be for you, as alſo that in diuers reſpects for number you are ten to one. And ſay in plaine tearmes,<note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> that it is not good <hi>in policy, to prouoke the Puritanes in the declyning of her Maieſties age and raigne.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XII. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>THE next diuiſion, he preferreth to no meaner perſonage, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne her ſelfe, in theſe teames. <hi>Let me preſent vnto your Maieſtie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>the whol num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your Subiects, diuided into</hi> 4. <hi>bands.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Proteſtants of Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Proteſtants of State.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Papiſts of State.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Papiſts of Religion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>What Logicke followeth after this diuiſion, is not to be ſounde in <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but ſo many Vntruthes bee maniſeſtlie ſounde in it, that I might make vp more
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17430:21"/>then my account in this place; but I may not wholy neglect ſo many and learned leſſons in the reſt of this <hi>Aſſociation.</hi> But co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this hacking and cutting the Subiects of England into thoſe 4. quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I muſte needes put this <hi>Iſocrates</hi> in minde, that he hath abuſed King <hi>Nicocles</hi> in this point. For <hi>Religion</hi> (eſpecially with thoſe which attribute ſo much to ſaith) is principally ſubiected in the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, then according to <hi>Plato,</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> his own Authors, it taketh ſpeciſica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion from ſuch things, as be taught and beleeued in Religion: and diuerſities of Religions muſt be named and diuided, according to the diuerſitie and multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of thinges beleeued: for as facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are diſtinguiſhed by their actes, ſo theſe are diuided and ſingled by their obiects, and not by the endes to which they be referred, or for which they bee practized; for this is the operation of the will, and not any action of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Then according to that which is prooned before, if there be almoſt 300. kindes of Proteſtants in other cuntreis, it is meruaile if only two had traficke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17430:22"/>Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.<note place="margin">Conuoc Lon. 1562. Parl. 5. Eliz. et 13. EliZ. Stow hiſt. Sinod. Lond. Artic. 1.2.3.4.5.7.26.</note> And to put him out of doubt the approoued booke of Articles, and two Parlaments, and our Proteſtant hiſtories do tell him, that in England &amp; among Engliſh Proteſtants, there bee <hi>Vigilantians, Neſtorians, Eutichians, Arrians, Eunomians, Grecians, Henricians, Iouinians, Donatiſts, Wicklefists, Berengarians, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Iulians, Aerians, Manichees, Browniſts, Barrowiſts, damned Crue,</hi> and I knowe not how many Crues of moſt wiched Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, &amp; himſelf remembreth ſome more.<note place="margin">Pag. 40.</note> Therefore his by-membred diuiſion of neceſſitie, is lame by many lims. And if ſuch a Tutor of Princes might haue a ſaculty by himſelfe, to renounce all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther artes, as his ſpirit condemneth all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religions: yet he ſhall finde many more endes then two of theſe which bee profeſſors of Reuerence in this Nation. And euery man which profeſſeth not Religion for the loue of God, is not of ſuch dexterity of wit, as this Puritane, and his <hi>Aſſociates</hi> be, to make it a cloake to practiſe in State affaires.<note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> Thirdlye, this princely pedagoge teacheth, that her Mareſtie her ſelfe, her Councell,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17430:22"/>Lords, Biſhops, Knights, and Burgeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parlament, be Papiſts, then the ſeconde member of his chiefe diuiſion <hi>(Proteſtants of State)</hi> is taken away, and he hath giuen himſelfe the contradiction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XIII VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>TO ſhew his cunning in conuerſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,<note place="margin">Pag. 11. 12.</note> he teacheth that <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (which be Puritanes) be firſt by order of generation, as his wordes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and Papiſts of Religion laſt, whoſe contrary is euident to al the world. Yet let vs allow greater meaſure to this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth. Next from Proteſtants of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, proceed Proteſtants of ſtate. From theſe Papiſts of eſtate bee rngendered. Laſtlye from theſe is the diſcent of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of Religion. And within ſiue lines after both forgetting himſelfe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of the doctrine of his Maſters, Plato, and Ariſtotle, and all reaſon which deny a regradation in cauſes, he acknowledgeth that Papiſts of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be Parents to al the reſt: The fourth, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17430:23"/>to the third, this, to the ſecond, the ſecond, of the firſt. Which in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer aſſertion gaue exiſtence to al. This is the ridle <hi>of Oedipus. Mater me genuit, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem mox gignitur ex me.</hi> But his only intent being to encreaſe the power of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of which hee conſidered before, ſeeketh by all meanes, true, or contrary, to make Puritaniſme the firſt and laſt: <hi>Alpha and Omega of all.</hi> As Philoſophers teache, <hi>that which is firſt by order of intention, is laſt by execution.</hi> And in this ſence his ſentence is true, for they wholie intend the ſetling of theyr Puritane ſect, which is their firſt and chiefeſt intention: But the ſetling, and execution thereof, by neceſſitie muſt be laſt: For both Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants and Catholikes muſt be taken out of theyt waye, before ſufficient ſcope and place be made for the Regiment of theyr ſpiritte, which as it ouer-turneth all thinges except it may rule the whole world, as the natural propenſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of enclineth, will euer be vnrulie, ſtill ſeeking Innouations.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:17430:23"/>
               <head>THE XIIII. VNTRVTH,</head>
               <p>AFter he hath ended his Diuiſions, in ſuch learned manner as I haue declared; he giueth cenſure of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertyes of the parts diuided. His defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue ſentence is this. <hi>The firſt (Puritanes) are conſtant and faithfull vnto your Highnes. The ſecond, (Proteſtants) wauerenge: The third,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>(Papiſts) of eſtate:</hi> (For ſuch he chargeth the Lordes, Biſhoppes, and others, of the laſt Parlament) <hi>perilous. The fourth, (Papiſts of Religion) Pernitious. Than the which nothinge can be more corrupt.</hi> I thinke this man ſhould meane, that <hi>Papiſts</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, be pernitious in reſpect of a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Regiment, for which he ſo much in words contendeth: Otherwiſe a falſe Religion (If we ſhould graunt our moſt holye Catholike Reuerence to be ſuch) being vſed of thoſe profeſſors, only for cauſe of Religion, (as his diſtinction is) cannot be offenſive or perilous to anye Ciuill Regiment againſt which it teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no repugnant thinge. Secondlye, he deſineth the inconuenience of theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17430:24"/>Papiſts of Religion, that (to vſe his wordes) <hi>they bee in Darknes, Falſe-hoode, Error, and Superſtition.</hi> Then ſeeing this member (of his diuiſion,<note place="margin">Pag. 11. 12. 13.</note> by his owne graunt) hath no reference to buſines of eſtate, they cannot be ofenſiue or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious, to that which they haue no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. But if hee coulde diſburthen themſelues (which will bee an heauye loade to doe,) if he will charge any of this guiltienes, the ſecond and thirde <hi>Proteſtants of eſtate, and Papiſts of eſtate,</hi> which often he confoundeth, becauſe he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotteth them to State affaires, muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into combat againſt him: Which they will eaſilye performe, being ſuch by his owne acknowledgment, as bee neareſte to her Maieſties Perſon,<note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> by Office, by Parlament, by Councell. And thoſe which haue not intermedling in ſuch matters, by the voice of ſo great an enemy, may not bee condemned as pernitious Aduerſaries. That mouth which denounceth them innocent in the firſt, cannot be admitted for Accuſer in the ſecond. Where no cauſe is prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or concommitant, no effecte can
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17430:24"/>be or followe, except an effect can bee cauſed without a cauſe. Thirdly, we are enfranchiſed by an other ſentence of this Cenſurer, for as he highly commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <hi>Proteſtants of Religion,</hi> or Puritanes, as <hi>conſtant</hi> and <hi>ſaithfull</hi> to our Queene,<note place="margin">Pag. 11.</note> ſo he confeſſeth that theſe be engendred of Proteſtants of eſtate, theſe of Papiſts of eſtate, which be ofspring to <hi>Papiſts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Then if there is any conſtancy or faithfulneſſe in the firſt, <hi>(Puritanes)</hi> as it muſt be doubled in the ſecond Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of eſtate, tripled in the third, ſo it muſt by that rule of proportion, be ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as conſtant and faithfull, in <hi>Papiſts of Religion:</hi> and by no meanes (if this mans gradation be true) can be leſſe in them, then in the other which proceede from them. My reaſon is (which this man may reade in his Authors <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi>) there be two kinde of cauſes, the one vniuocall, the other equiuocall: the firſt although it is not that which is now in queſtion, yet it muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ſo much vertue as the effect which it produceth: otherwiſe ſome vertue in that which is cauſed ſhould bee effected
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17430:25"/>without cauſe, which is a deceaſance in nature. Of this ſort be all inferiour na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall agents as men, beaſtes, fowles, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, &amp;c. which produce the like in their kinde. The ſecond (of which condition this Pamphletors diſcent and progeny is to be eſteemed) is called Equiuocall which euer contayneth more vertue and ability, then that which is effected; in which ſence the Sunne, Heauens, and God himſelfe, are termed ſuch equiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and vniuerſall or generall cauſes; becauſe their power ſo much excelleth the faculties of their particuler effects: and are able to bring forth many and not only one, or few operations. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by an other free charter of this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, <hi>Papiſts of Religion</hi> are freed from al ſuſpect to bee pernitious, or any wayes dangerous in this buſines: becauſe they want all thoſe helpes by which he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Power and ſtrength of any people is to bee augmented.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> 1. <hi>addition or number.</hi> 2. <hi>ſupply of Neceſſaries.</hi> 3. <hi>aduantage of place.</hi> 4. <hi>order of gouernment.</hi> All which, be wanting in that people, as is before demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Puritanes be poſſeſſed of them
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17430:25"/>all. And touching his addition, &amp; num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which hee nameth for the chiefeſt ſupplie, himſelf acknowledgeth, that in the beginning of her Maieſties raigne,<note place="margin">Pag. 40.</note> when <hi>we were many and mighty,</hi> we were ſo farre from contriuing againſt her, that we honoured her with her greateſt dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Diademe it ſelfe. Then there can be no daunger hereafter. For ſeing our doctrine is one, there is no ſuch pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill of diuerſity in dealings in that caſe. And to auoide vs from all ielouſie, for ſuture and preſent times, he maketh this threatning calculation,<note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> howe in diuers reſpects, Puritanes are ten times more, and mightier then Proteſtants. Howe farre this ſorte exceedeth all kindes of Papiſts, there is no doubt. And yet it pleaſeth this man to acknowledge this ſentence.<note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>It is not vnprobahle, that of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in this Land, the fourth part are not Papiſts of Religion.</hi> Then it cannot be truly ſaid, that ſuch people be pernitious, or peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in this Common wealth: which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all their poſitions agreeable to an honourable and ciuill Regiment, their orderly, dutifull, &amp; quiet conditions in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17430:26"/>
                  <hi>Saxonye, Denmarke,</hi> ſome cantons of <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland, Greece, Hungary, Turkic, Perſia,</hi> and other places where they liue vnder Prin ces, enemies to their Religion, will be an eternall euidence. When contrariewiſe theſe Puritanes &amp; <hi>Proteſtants of Religion, So conſtant and faithfull to her Maieſtye,</hi> (if this mans word be <hi>Goſpell:</hi>)<note place="margin">Mart Mar Prel.</note> not only be their priuate ſeditious Libels without ende in England, but factious Admonitions by their generall acclamation to our <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Parlament,</hi> by publickly defended po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiitions, that <hi>the lawes of Princes doe not binde in conſcience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Andrew. Will. Sinop. c. lawes. Calu. inſt. Foxe. to 2. ſup. obed. Tind. art. 18. Claud. de Sanct. lib. 5. accad egl.</note> 
                  <hi>that eucrie man is Lord of other mens goods, the children of faith,</hi> (which bee onely Puritanes in their opinion) <hi>are vnder no lawe, all humane lawes muſt be taken away, the nature of the Goſpell is to raiſe wars, among Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, there is no Magiſtrate, no Superiour:</hi> and whoſe practiſe in action hath euer beene anſwerable to this doctrine, manifeſte by all monuments of theyr proceedings, or rather to be reprooued for ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitious and perilous people.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:17430:26"/>
               <head>THE XV. VNTRVTH,</head>
               <p>BVT to ſhewe how high a pitch of impiety he can mount, to make a malitious ſtoope vpon men in miſery, he vttereth this moſt foule and vntrue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. <hi>The Papiſts of Religion at this preſent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 25.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtand furniſhed</hi> 1. <hi>with credit and authority,</hi> 2. <hi>wealth and ability,</hi> 3 <hi>weapons and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: So that they may drawe followers by the one, wage them by the other, and arme them by the third.</hi> Whould any man thinke, that ſo holy, wiſe, and well affected friend, as this man woulde ſee me to her Maieſty, durſt preſent ſo monſtrous and palpable an vntruth, to the viewe of of ſo prudent a <hi>Priuceſſe,</hi> but that I haue alleadged his owne wordes. For the firſt of credit &amp; authority, I thinke it a difficult thing, for this Puritane to find one Cathohcke in England, which hath any authority at all. Let him name any Preſedent of Wales, or the North, Warden of Ports, Gouernour of Ilandes, Captaine of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Lieuetenant of Tower, Lieuete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Deputy-Lieuetenant, Sheriffe.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17430:27"/>Iuſtice of peace, or poore Conſtable, or Tythingman, which is a Papiſt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. I thinke it will be a diſſicult thing for him, to ſinde in our whole kingdome tenne of the meaneſt authority which I haue named. Of the chiefeſt no man can be ſingled ſorth. What the wealth and ability of them can be, except God doth miraculouſlie bleſſe them (then let not Puritanes repine at his benediction) who can imagine, if he ſee the due pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of 260. poundes yearely paide to her Maicſties Checker by the chiefeſt, and by other the two partes of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenewes moſte truely anſwered, their goods ſeaxed; and beſides theſe, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny extraordinary oppreſsions by Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes in authority. As for weapons, and ſurniture, to arme ſo many as would ſight againſt ſo many thouſands of <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes of action,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> and <hi>reſolution, of London and good Towner, moſt Lords, Gentlemen, and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines,</hi> which be for them, is a thing ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſlie vntrue, that none or ſewe Catholickes be poſſeſſed of any at all. Doth he not remember when they were diſpoyled of them. And to this day are
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17430:27"/>ſcarcely (where ſuch Muſter Maſters liue) admitted to haue vſe of their owne to ſerue her Maieſty. And at the time of the comming of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> when ſomewhat more was in hand then Catholickes imagined, were they not generally in the Weſt cuntries ſo diſpoiled by puritane Iuſtices of their ordinary Armes, &amp; weapons, that they were in danger to be ſpoyled of the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt Robbers for want of ſufficient de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt them. but if theſe three thinges be thoſe that bee ſo perilous in people apt for Innouations, let him look into Puritanes, and howe many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fands he may finde furniſhed with thoſe complements.<note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> His owne ſentence <hi>(Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and good Townes, most Lordes, Gentlemen, and Captames of action and reſolution)</hi> will be ſufficient cenſure againſt him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17430:28"/>
               <head>THE XVI. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>AT the laſt, this <hi>Aſſociator</hi> commeth to iſſue, and ſomewhat vnmasketh himſelfe, to giue teſtimony to his ſpirit, to diſpoſe of the Crowne, make his Queene a Pupill, expell Catholickes, roote out Proteſtantes, wholly to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance his Puritane Goſpell, &amp; to bring the Scepter and Regality of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, <note place="margin">Pag. 18.</note> to the ſacred diſpoſition of their ſpirit. His wordes are theſe. <hi>The migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt in ſucceſsion (as your Maieſtie knoweth) are they</hi> (ſpeaking in the plurall number) <hi>whoſe alliance, kindred, and confederacies, are for the moſt part with Papists:</hi> Who is igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant this to be a notorious Vntruth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept hee will aduance any Title from Spaine, and then his plurall number wil except againſt him: otherwiſe if al thoſe which be next in ſucceſsion, muſt be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as Papiſts, and worthy of diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance from all Title of a Kingdome, by the ſupreame ſentence of their ſpirit, becauſe they be not Puritanes, either a Puritane whether hee hath any Title
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17430:28"/>or no muſt raigne. Or (which is more probably to be coniectured) where theſe deſires ſhould be effected of depriuing true Titlers from their inheritance, and Puritaniſme ſhall haue ſuperiority, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland ſhall haue no King, Queene, or Regent at all. And if her Maieſty ſhould attend to ſuch treacherous, and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall ſuggeſtions as this ſpirit enſpireth, and their purpoſe of planting their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety be performed, ſhee were like to be rewarded, with the ſame payment of their common doctrine which I cited before, <hi>that the children of faith are vnder no lawe. That there is no Magiſtrate, no Superiour among Chriſtians. All humane lawes muſt bee taken away. Eueryman is Lorde of other mens goods,</hi> and the like muſt bee put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe. The presbitery which they would haue planted in Scotland to the depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of their King.<note place="margin">Kinge of Scots in his Booke of Reg. to Henry his Sonne. Suru. of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly diſciple.</note> The practiſe of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua and ſuch places, for a fewe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and yearly elected Artizans to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, and the Flemmiſh faſhion muſt be erected. And none but Puritanes and their vile deuiſes haue allowance, which this ſeditious libeller doth plainly
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17430:29"/>inſinuate in the nexte page following:<note place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> where he giueth this for a lawe to our gratious Queene, to vſe both Puritanes and Proteſtants, for the planting of his platforme of Reſormation; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing effected her Maieſtie muſte (to vſe his owne wordes) <hi>by ſcuere diſcipline migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely encreaſe the firſt (Puritanes) daylie to demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſecond and third (Proteſtants and Papiſts) and to propulſe the relapſes of either.</hi> So that the affections of theſe fellowes (as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues giue ſentence) tende to the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwe of Proteſtant, as well as Papiſt, And the number of the one, equally as of the other muſt be diminiſhed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed. So that whatſoeuer they are, Queene, Councell, Nobility, Lawes, Parlament, Authority, or any procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, not reſined by the ſpirit of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes, muſt be thus diminiſhed and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne. This (as I ſaide beſore) was their firſt intention, and nowe is their finall end.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17430:29"/>
               <head>THE XVII. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>ANd that theſe <hi>Pretendors of perſection in Religion</hi> (as this <hi>Aſsociator</hi> calleth Puritanes) might pretend a perfect and abſolute neglect and reiectment of al or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,<note place="margin">Pag. 24.</note> Magiſtracy, and Regiment, in this Kingdome: After they had ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſted their ſugred mouthes, with the vnpleaſing ſauors of the State and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, as they complained both in their ſo much diſhked Bill of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this Author conſeſſeth in his <hi>Aſsociotion.</hi> They firſt apealed to Parla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp; taking the repulſe in that high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt authoritiue Conſiſtorye, beſiedge our Soueraygne with ſuche gloſles, as haue beene recited of her danger by Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and theyr onely tender care of her happineſſe and prſeruation. Hopeing perhaps ſhe would for their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narye loue, rewarde them with thoſe extraordinarye graces of her abſolute power, which by vſual meanes ſhee had omitted, Now in this part of their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociation, rather then they will be lefte
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17430:30"/>deſolate of all helpes, they will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeale from Parlament and Prince, to the Proteſtant Biſhoppes, (a parcell thereof) but vnite them-ſelues with them in all loue and fraternitye, whome in ſo manye Rimes, Libelles, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uectues, they haue diſgraced ſo many yeares together. And ſalute them in theyr firſte entrance with Tytles of <hi>the moſt Reuerend Arch-biſhops, and right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Logd Biſhops,</hi> to whome in all former proceedings, they haue euer and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely denyed all <hi>Reuerence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Lordeſhippe,</hi> and the common name of eyther <hi>Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop,</hi> or the other. And now plainely acknowledge them to haue power to performe that which Queene and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leament had denied.<note place="margin">Pag. 24.</note> And yet they ſtill reſerue a laſte appeale to the higheſte courte of all, which is theyr ſpiritte, to threaten ouer-matchinge multitudes,<note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> and ſtrength, bothe for number, and power; if theyr griefes be not redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Firſte, they complaine that theyr Bill againſte Catholickes was not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in Parlament. The cauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſ, they would eſtabliſhe, with a moſte
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17430:30"/>vnſtable falſehoode, <hi>by the Papiſts packing</hi> (to vſe their wordes) <hi>to make Burgeſses for this Parleament.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> How true a tale it is? or can by poſsible coniecture bee: Who but ſuch truſty <hi>Prophets</hi> can diuine? who be they which be in Parlament? of what eſtates, places, callings? who, and what authority doth aſſemble them? is not euery Parlament called by our Queenes authority? is ſhee a Papiſt? are the Councell Papiſts? are the Lordes Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts?<note place="margin">Pag. 41.</note> in an other place hee ſaith they moſt are for them. Are the Sheriffes of Shires, the Iuſtices, and others, which make the choiſe of Knights Papiſts? no Papiſt is admitted to thoſe offices. Are not London, and the Townes whence the Burgeſſes be, as this man ſaith, Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes? are the Proteſtant Biſhops and Clergy, Papiſts? and yet theſe bee they, of whome that Parlament conſiſted, and in whome, of all others, Papiſts haue the leaſt intereſt. Therefore if that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of ſpeech, and Alehouſe phraſe of <hi>Packing,</hi> were as lawefull for me, as pack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, playing, ieſting, and wicked ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt dealings be vſuall with theſe men,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17430:31"/>euen towards Peeres and Princes; wee could neither packe, ſhuffle, or cut, in that Parlament. Neither was there any motiue to incite vs to ſuch exerciſes; for firſt, there was no Bill to bee preferred for our good. And none but Puritanes (of whoſe counſaile wee are not) did thinke that ſuch meaſure would be then offered againſt vs. But moſt likely it is, that this people, which had ſo long, as this Pamphlet ſeemeth, to inſinuate by the phraſe <hi>(long ſince penned)</hi> both deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined that vnnaturall Bill,<note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> this <hi>Aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and all miſchiefe they coulde ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, to afflicted Catholickes. And if banding to gither for that intent, ſolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing Queene, Nobles, Clergy, and Burgeſſes, and ſhuffling themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the meaneſt Romes, rather then their voyces ſhould be wanting may be tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Packing:</hi> the packing was in them, and not in vs. As alſo the number of their Goſpell, noted to be farre greater in that, then any former Parlament will witneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:17430:31"/>
               <head>THE XVIII. VNTRVTH,</head>
               <p>BVT this man is not aſhamed to tearme all that reſiſted their Bill, to be Papiſts. Theſe be his wordes. <hi>I call them Papiſts,<note place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> which were ſo carnest againſt that Bill. For who but Papiſts, would pronounce that Penalty to be extreame, &amp;c. But their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and dangerous end, doth manifeſt them to be Papiſts.</hi> Hitherto be his owne wordes. Which how vntrue they be, that thoſe Lordes, Biſhops, Knightes, and Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes which reiected that Bill (which were the whole Parlament, and all En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland repreſented in that maior parte let others cenſure. Onely I humblie wiſh ſuch Papiſts, which be all ſorts and eſtates of people in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, Soueraigne, and Subiects, which be not <hi>Puritanes, and pretendors of their perfection in Religion,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of theſe mens ſpirit. For although they be not Papiſts, yet ſeeing it pleaſeth their ſpirit to condemne them by the names of <hi>Papiſts, Popiſh, and dangerous:</hi> they are not vnlike to taſte of the ſame cup with Papiſts, if euer theſe <hi>Aſſociators</hi> may
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17430:32"/>haue their will. And although thoſe thinges which I now alleadge, be diuers and diſtinct vntruthes to this I haue ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet becauſe in reckoning ſo ſmall a number of this mans forgeries, I muſte ouer-paſſe many of moment; and theſe following make for this purpoſe, that all Proteſtants, either of the Lay or Clergy condition, Magiſtrates of what calling ſoeuer, which be not at the becke of Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes, to aduance their pleaſures, are in the caſe of Papiſtry, and equally ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Catholike Recuſants themſelues: this Religious pretendor of perfection, acknowledgeth it to be their ſentence, when he breaketh out in theſe ſpeeches. <hi>The Pope can diſpence with Papiſts their beeing Miniſters in our Churches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>prouided, they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſome one point of Popery or other. With their being Magiſtrates in our Common wealth, prouided, they vnder hand, hinder proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Papiſts.</hi> Which two ſentences, the firſt moſt falſe, and the ſecond not nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſpenſation, being a lawfull act, yet they prooue, how Puritanes eſteeme all, both Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Proteſtant Clergy, as alſo
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17430:32"/>all Magiſtrates (no degree excepted) which in any reſpect oppoſe themſelues to the headlong actions of this people, to be Papiſts and ſo to bee puniſhed by their ſpirit, if euer it be in their power to performe it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XIX. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>VVIll anye man beleeue him to tell a truthe, when to gloſſe their wiched practizes, he both denieth the Earle of Eſſex to be a Puritane:<note place="margin">Pag. 28.</note> and affirmeth that he was ledde by Papiſts to that diſobedient tumult. And yet he bluſheth not to ſay that Doleman in his Epiſtle, doth cunninglye in ſinuate and adviſe to make him awaie. When there is not anye one worde in that Epiſtle to that purpoſe; or to arme him to anye diſobedience, except the ſpirit of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taues doth iudge: If anye affirmeth a Nobleman is in credit with Prince and popular with the people, (as all men knew he was; and is that which Dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man there ſpeaketh) is a warrante to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17430:33"/>make ſuch a tumulte as he did. Neither can the Earle be ſaide to be ledde or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Papiſts, except he will now giue that name a more ample ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion then he did before, and make it alſo comprehenſiue of theyr owne ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le bretheren, and pretendors of perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Religion, as is before deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed. And whether himſelf was ſuch, or a Papiſt. Examine the lamentable and repininge wordes, actions, geſtures, and beehauiors of all Puritanes at the time of his deſolate ende: Demaunde the Pulpits of Puritanes, which ſo much deplored him. And let any Puritane if he can, exemplify one man, either a Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or led in that wickedneſſe, which by any probability had euer counſaile of I eſuite, or Prieſt to that enterpriſe. But that theſe, and all Catholickes, both condemned the facte, and reioyced at her Maieſties deliuery. Which ſoone after, and euer ſince, manye of them, eſpecially in the Weſterne countries, haue dearely bought at the handes of Puritanes in authority And vpon the very day, and at the very houre (as was
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17430:33"/>ſuppoſed) of his death (namely and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerallly in Summerſet Shire, where a Prince of theſe pretendors of perfection raigneth, and of whoſe pure breath this Pamphlet ſauoureth) al houſes of Catho lickes were forcibly entred, with great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers conducted by Puritane leaders, &amp; without any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion ſhewed, rifled, ranſacked, and ſpoyled, without reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch iniuries. And the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke, and other poſſeſſors of thoſe how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, both baſely vſed, and threatned at home, and in contumelious tearmes &amp; vſage committed to priſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XX. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>NOW this holy pretending Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peller, is come to diſgorge his poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, againſt the Reuerend, and Sacred Prieſts of our Nation: and principally, of the moſt learned, and holy Society of Ieſus. Whome he doth not only charge, with diſloyall practiſes againſt the State of this Kingdome, but (which is moſte impudent) inuenteth ſhameles ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17430:34"/>as though ſuch things had bin both prooued againſt them by ſome Prieſtes of England, and themſelues had voutſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the accepta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thoſe accuſations,<note place="margin">Pa. 29. 30. 31. 32. 33. 34. 35. 36. 37.</note> by thier ſilence of not making anſwere to ſuch crimes. And going forwarde in this bluſhleſſe buſineſſe, laboureth to perſwade the Reader, that the Ieſuites and ſome Prieſts (ſuch as haue appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) conuented and agreed togither, to counterfeit a contention betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to this purpoſe, that the Ieſuites beeing but few in number, and not able by that diſparity, to aduance the cauſe of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, as thoſe Prieſts which bee not of their ſociety, a farre greater multitude will willingly vndergoe the ignominy of all miſdeamenors obiected: and ſet the Prieſts at freedome, for the intent reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. And that the Pope himſelfe hath diſpenced in theſe conſpiracies. Which horrible ſinnes be ſuch, and ſo odious in Catholicke Reuerence, to ſuffer and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence in a voluntary infamy, not onely in particular perſons, daily bequeathed to death for their Religion, but of ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed a fraternity, that no man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17430:34"/>refined and purified with that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, with which no fraude, falſehood, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing, or treachery can be ſinne, will poſsibly imagine. But to call this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man backe againe to ſo many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect vntruthes, which he hath vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this diſcourſe, I doubt not but ſince the writing of his Pamphler, hee perceaueth <hi>defacto,</hi> that thoſe which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed that company of Ieſuites, by <hi>Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libets,</hi> and I knowe not what, were not ſuch Prieſts, and friends to Ieſuites, as he excepteth againſt them: But if I may dilate the worde <hi>Puritane,</hi> halfe ſo farre as he extendeth <hi>Papiſt,</hi> it will appeare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to his dimme ſight, that almoſt <hi>Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet</hi> was agent in <hi>Quodlibet.</hi> And that all Appellants vtterly diſclaymed from thoſe bookes. Touching your vntruth, that the Ieſuites yeelded to thoſe crimes and accuſers, you haue alſo ſeene howe foulie you were deceaued. And for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence to her Maieſty, and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Councel, I muſt ſpare you too much in theſe points.</p>
               <p>And S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, Pretendor <hi>of Perſection,</hi> in this place you were deceaued in raſhe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17430:35"/>that there was no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the Ieſuites and ſome Prieſtes. And it is neither ſin, nor ſhame to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, being but matter <hi>de facto, not any queſtion</hi> of <hi>Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and ſuch as beſides your daily chops and changes, controuerſies, and contentions in higheſt miſteries, &amp; matters of Reuerence: the Courtes of lawe, where perfect brethren daily im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleade one an other, will giue recorde, that at this preſent, there be many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, and in theſe times, haue beene thouſands of greater diſſention, then that only one in ſo many yeares, when no Superiour or Conſiſtory, for the Prieſts of our Nation, was to determine any contention. Your wiſedome hath definitiuely ſet downe in your <hi>Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that the only reaſon why Ieſuites, &amp; Prieſts, be ſo dangerous people in this Nation, is, becauſe they hope for future aduauncements by alterations: And therefore practiſe enen the death it ſelfe of our Soueraigne. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, to pleade expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience (the Maſter of fooles) her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty is the eldeſt Engliſh <hi>Princeſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew hiſt. Graft hiſt.</note> ſince the Normans entred; ſhee hath raigned 44.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:17430:35"/>yeares complete. And yet ſuch wiſe men as you haue daily vſed theſe acclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt vs. But the euent hath proued how perilous we are, neuer any prince reigned halfe ſo longe wher your Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is admitted. Secondly your ſelfe may eaſely vnderſtand that in the order of the Ieſuits there is a rule, indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by any of their ſociety, <hi>not to meddle in matters of eſtate.</hi> Thirdly,<note place="margin">Sil. v. Irre: Fum. v. irr. Nau. v. irr. ſum. Caiet. Panormit. tollet. v ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>egular. &amp;c.</note> the Canons of Catholicke Religion repute it ſo greate an vnworthineſſe, for any Prieſt to bee guilty of the death of the meaneſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iccte, that all ſuch bee <hi>ipſo facto Irregular,</hi> and diſabled to execute that ſacred fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. Then what will it be eſteemed, to be guilty of Princes bloud? And S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, to diſpute of ſuch ambitious ends, as you woulde prognoſticate they haue deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined: So vniuerſall a man as you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be reputed, cannot be vnskilfull, how this ſo much offenſiue Society hath made it ſelfe ſo farre vncapable of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and aduauncements, that the whole Chriſtian worlde reporteth for a nouelty when any Cardinall or Biſhop, is created from that company: although
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17430:36"/>for all kindes of ſuch deſeruings, all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions will witneſſe, how worthy they are of greateſt dignities. And if you vvill trauaile, at the leaſt with your vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, into <hi>Italy, Spayne, Germany, Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Bohemia,</hi> the <hi>Indies,</hi> and other nations where they liue, you ſhall eaſely make experiment, and (except you leaue your will behinde wholly poſſeſſed with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice) acknowledge, that thoſe Ieſuites which be now in England, when they liued in ſuch forraigne Nations, both were ſreed from theſe perils which they paſſe in their owne countrey, and yet en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyed as much as England Catholickes would, or can allowe them. The eſtate of their countrey, and fellowe brethren left behinde in ſuch condition, will tell you, what exchange fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> better to worſe, the Ieſuites at home haue made. Thoſe Kingdomes nowe Catholicke, giue with ſecurity and reputation, ſo much, as with ſo many dangers and reproches, any fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture time can yeelde them hope, which is nothing, but <hi>S. Pauls victus and veſtitus,</hi> with which they are, and muſt bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. Then who can cenſure them to be
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17430:36"/>ſo greate fauourites to ſorreigners ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uancements, and careleſſe of their owne ſecurities for no greater gaine? Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning other renerende Prieſtes of this Kingdome, as you thunder not againſt them with ſo greate fury, ſo I truſte of many late defences, ſome will come to your handes, and as they be innocent, ſo be an armour to ſaue them harmeleſſe, and for that reaſon I may, and for other regardes I muſt be ſilent. And you may reſt ſecure, that the Monkes of <hi>S. Benc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts</hi> order, are not yet multiplied to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes your Abbies: Ten or ſuch like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, are not likely in haſte, to challenge and enjoy, ſo many hundreds of Monaſteries with their reuenewes, as were their dowrie in England. And ſo ſmall an handfull of other Prieſts, are not likely to make preſent entry to ſo many thouſands of Biſhoprickes, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neries, and Eccleſiaſticali liuings, as the Proteſtant Clergy is ſetled in. Many or moſt of vs, haue willingly diſinheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our ſelues, and embraced wantes; we which haue beene voluntaries in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty ſo long, cannot by probability, be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17430:37"/>ſo ſodainely changed to deſire riches, with ſo greate encombers. If England were Catholicke to morrowe, no <hi>Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of perfection</hi> euer heard, that in any age, ſuch a generallity of <hi>Dualities,</hi> or <hi>Plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> was grannted, which coulde endowe ſo litte a number, with ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſpirituall maintenances. Then S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, if you coulde bee but ſo equally affected to them, which were ſo many hundred yeares togither, true Titlers, and ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, both of Religion, and religious poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions in this Nation, to let them now, in ſome poore diſgraced and penitentiall manner profeſſe the firſt, with ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion as they affect: they ſhould eaſely ioyne to leaue the ſecond, to them which more deſire, and leſſe deſerue it. And I truſt no Puritane ſhould complaine of perill to Prince, iniury to himſelfe, or dammage to other ſubiect. Such ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of God (which is all wee ſeeke) is not ſo dangerous eiher to Religion <hi>eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,</hi> or the temporall ſtate of our moſt beloued countrey, that any banding in <hi>Aſſociations</hi> be needefull againſt it. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither more or ſo much as the Pope
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17430:37"/>himſelfe alloweth to the Iewes in all his Terrytories, euen in the City of Rome, where he is Reſiant. And which the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prines of Germany, the Turkiſh Emperour, Perſian, and other abſolute Monarches (which cannot be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned regardleſſe of their temporall Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) allowe vnto Ieſuites, Prieſtes, and others both religious, and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes of the Lay condition: in vvhich ſo ſmall a kindneſſe, any man of reaſon, woulde rather preſume vpon your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, then feare your disfriendſhippe. And the rather becauſe (S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> giue mee leaue) in this very Pamphlet, ſo inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiue againſt ſo little curteſie, your ſelfe doe ſeeme to free vs of all vnworthines. For if you remember, there be but two bars which you put againſt it, (Ielouſie to concur with forreigne forces) (And Popes Supremacy with reconciliation) and your ſelfe haue broken both, and ſeeme to ſet vs at liberty from ſuch ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects. Of the former, thus you doe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge vs, when you take away all hope of aduancements, by ſuch conſpirings, (vpon which you ground your wicked
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17430:38"/>and vntrue conceits) your acquittance in this caſe is ſet downe in theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Pag. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>The Admirant of Arragon, ſpared the Papiſts no more, then the other in the Borders of Germany. And the Duke of Medina ſaid, that if he had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed againſt England with his inuincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado, he would haue ſpared Papiſts, no more then Proteſtants, but make way for his Maſter.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſecond, our <hi>Supercedias</hi> from you,<note place="margin">Pag. 35.</note> may bee this ſentence. <hi>Prieſtes</hi> are executed <hi>(indeede)for affirming the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and reconciling to the Church of Rome, which are partes of their Prieſtly function.</hi> Then S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, if <hi>Supremacy in the Pope of Rome, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceconcile to that Church, be partes of Prieſtly fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> which is wholly ſpirituall and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinct from a ciuill ſtate, and temporall affaires: by no lawe or learning, that which appertayneth to that function, &amp; is parte thereof, can bee preiudiciall or dangerous to the ſecond. And your ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diſtinction following, which you ſay was made before the late Earle of Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington, (you are well acquainted with that family, watch-wordes, ward-words and their appendices) that <hi>Prieſtes are not executed for theſe partes, as they are religious, but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17430:38"/>as they bee dangerous to the State, in ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration:</hi> is both ridiculous for my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before, and derogareth to the lawes of England: becauſe you cannot doubt but thoſe articles were maintayned, known, and honured euen in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, by almoſt 200. Kinges and their lawes, many hundreds of yeares togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vntill theſe daies: &amp; at this preſent, are ſo reuerenced in the moſt floriſhing Kingdomes of the worlde. And if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention be betweene Religions, and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill lawes (except God be inferiour to man) it is no queſtion who muſte haue dominion. Temporall thinges be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinat to ſpirituall. Religion is the higheſt rule. But to giue you all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment;<note place="margin">Pag. 6. 7.</note> if you only muſt bee vviſe, and your plots approoued; Then to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisſie you in your owne deviſes of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which be by oath, and pecuniary puniſhments: Concerning the laſte, I haue made you a reckoning before, how the Catholickes of England which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their Religion, anſwer yearely, &amp; truly farre greater ſummes to her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties vſe for that cauſe, then, you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande:
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:17430:39"/>If they come not to her purſe, you knowe they be not ſuch Recuſants which be Receauers and hinder it. And for other Subiects, how no gaine at all, but generall diſcontent would grow, by tender of ſuch oathes, your owne opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo often repeated of Parlament and diſguiſed Papiſts, ouerthroweth your firſt poſition, and woulde prooue the practiſe to be ridiculous. Touching an oath for the ſecurity of our moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Queene, and the temporall eſtate of this kingdome, a man of ſuch reading as you affect to bee reputed, doth knowe, that a ſpirituall oath was neuer vſed in any Nation, to ſecure a ciuill Regiment: Neither by any wit, can you nowe make it a politicke inuention for that purpoſe. Where the endes be diuers, the meanes muſt needes be different. But ſeeing it pleaſeth you thus farre to giue confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to the conſciences of Catholickes (which is more then we dare aſſume for you) Then if you remember vvhat is written,<note place="margin">Pag. 6. 7.</note> both in domeſticall, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigne hiſtories commended, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in lawes of Princes, to ſuch
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17430:39"/>ſntents. Temporall Regiments are, and euer were ſecured, both in this, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations, by oathes of temporall, and ciuill duty, and obedience. To this, our ancient Statutes, and the particular oathes of priuate offices, as of generall, and common allegeance be teſtimony, Then S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, to ſecure our Prince, and trie our aſſections, if you mooue our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne to receaue all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihkes into her protection, which will take ſuch oath, which is ſo much as we euer gaue to former Prince, or our lawes require, or her Maieſty (will as I hope) needeth to demande, let all which refuſe ſo louing, and gratious dealings, be as in all former ages, forth of her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and defence. And whereas your newe engin is, that oathes, ſhoulde bee chieflie miniſtred to Gentlemen, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, and Poſſeſsionors,<note place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> by which particular you knowe how many be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted, yet to take all danger of your perilous Prieſts, and Ieſuites away, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, that vpon their acceptance of this, and rheir allegeance ſworne, they may be diſcharged from your Inuectiues,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17430:40"/>ſlanders, and other hazardes. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you change opinions ſo often, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny newe eonceite of ſcruple, ſhall make you newly perplexed, that they will not deale ſincerely: Let them be put to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure this, with a ſeconde vvarrant, of known, and ſufficient ſureties. And I do not doubt, but both Ieſuites, &amp; Prieſts, will as willingly accept, and truely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme that oath, and with as great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to all, finde as ample, and able pledges, as Puritanes can doe, either for their duties to Soueraigne, or debts to Subiects: which we truſt, the innocency of our behauiour, and creditte in that cauſe, with ſuch as wil be taken for grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters, ſhall procure; if the danger and diſgrace, to giue aſſurance for ſuch perſons, &amp; in ſuch a caſe, be taken away. And to put a perpetuall barre betweene you, and all future feare of our forreigne Seminaries, and dealings for other Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if a man of your direction could, and would procure vnto vs, ſo much grace with our moſt gratious Queene, to tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerate in this Kingdome, but a fevve Schooles, for the education of Students,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17430:40"/>and to allowe but the leaſt number of Catholicke Biſhops, to ſacre the Prieſts of our Nation, I am out of doubt, you ſhall ſee, that we will moſt willingly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne all penſions, ſtipends, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances, from ſtrange Princes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though out of ſo many hundreds of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious houſes, and thouſands of ſpirituall liuings, our ancient patrimony, your be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence giueth vs nothing at all. And if you haue confidence in your cauſe, that your Religion is true, let our Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges be in your Vniuerſities, whoſe ancient conſtitutions we will obſerue, &amp; triall will ſooner be made, whether Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes or Papiſts defend the better wor ſhippe: And if you dare not deale in that (as I am ſecured you will not, which we wil grant to you in Catholicke Schooles, but you neuer durſt grant the one, or accept the other) allotte our aboade, to meaner and obſcurer places. By this meanes, and ſuch oathes as you maye tender, and ſecurity offered, all our tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke, and ſuſpecte of concourſe with Spaine, Spaniſh, or any enemy will bee taken away. And to put you in ſome
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17430:41"/>hope of indee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnity by ſuch proceedings, looke into Saxony, and other countries where this is vſed, and you ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a long continued vnity for many yeares paſt, no ſuſpicion at this preſent, or danger for times to come. O S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>, doe you thinke any Engliſh Catholicke can beſo vnnaturall or fooliſh (if he hath but common wit, which I hope you will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe to our labours, learning, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes) to deſire to liue vnder a forraigne Regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, if he may liue at home, though in diſhonour our daily returning into England to your tortures, from ſecurity abroad, is teſtimony vnto our ſincerity. I take the whole court of heauen to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I am, and euer was. farre from wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing, and I thinke, there is neither Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, nor Prieſt in England which deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth it: It was an olde ſaying, and prayer of my father when I was a childe, <hi>that we might ſpeake Engliſh ſtill,</hi> and ſhall euer bee the opinion of his ſonne. And if your Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane factions be not greater hazard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, then any practiſe of Papiſt, I truſt we ſhall enioy it. I haue bin more bolde to acquaint you with theſe things:
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17430:41"/>firſt, becauſe a great number of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Prieſts, &amp; Ieſuites, haue vndertaken thoſe holy functions, by occaſion of your Puritane moſt vnholy dealings and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions againſt them, euen to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ilement into thoſe Nations. Secondly, (becauſe I loue to anſwere you with your owne Arguments) in reſpect you graunt it a thing vniuſt,<note place="margin">Pag. 35.</note> that Prieſts ſhoulde bee put to death, or perſecuted, for affirming the <hi>Popes Supremacy, &amp; reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciling to the Church of Rome, which are parts of their Prieſtly functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> for if this ſecurity (which is all you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande) were giuen, they coulde not bee <hi>dangerous to the State, in ciuill conſideration,</hi> though wee appeale to your iudgement. Thirdly, becauſe (if wee ſhoulde graunt all your vntruthes, and ſlanders againſte Prieſts, and Ieſuites, to be the higheſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) yet in your whole Pamphlet, you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer charge any one Prieſt, or Ieſuite in particuler, which is in England, to bee guilty of any ſuch conſpiracy,<note place="margin">Pag. 33. Proclam. 5. Nouemb. 1562.</note> excepte (perhaps) <hi>Doctor Bagſhawe</hi> (whome with many others the late Proclamation of her Maieſty her ſelfe excuſeth) but you loade the ſhoulders of ſuch as conuerſed in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17430:42"/>Nations,<note place="margin">Pag. 33. Pag. 27. 30. 33.</note> as the late <hi>Cardinall Allen, D. Briſtowe, D. Sanders, Father Parſons, and Father Walpoole,</hi> to be the Agents in ſuch buſines, neither can I, or any man of equal ſentence, perceaue how a priuate Prieſt in Englande, lining vnder ſuch watchfull cies, can carry the leaſt ſuſpicion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire with externe Princes. Or what pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Prieſt, durſt broach ſuch an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe to any Ieſuite, Prieſt, or Catholike in this Kingdome? or who woulde harken vnto him, if hee wereſo deſperate to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it? And if you can, name that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, or Prieſt, the <hi>Arch-prieſt, Prouinciall of the Ieſuites, or any Prieſt</hi> of their obedience, which haue delt in ſuch conſpiracies: why are you ſilent only in that, and ſo prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall in all other kindes of accuſall. Good Sir, vtter your owne name, and that Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite or Prieſt in England, whome you haue moſt confidence to accuſe, ſet downe the fact and offence, againſt this preſent ſtate in ciuil conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and I doubt not, but he wil acquit himſelf to your confuſion &amp; ſhame. Therefore if this lawe coulde bee enacted by yoru interceſsion, our gratious Queene, Councell, and whole State,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17430:42"/>might ſleepe in ſecuritie by your own ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, except the ruffling windes of your Puritane ſpirit ſhould awake thee<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if you ſhould be yet perplexed, that ſo ſmall a number of Ieſuites, and Prieſts, liuing in ſo diſgraced conditions, by their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and example of regular life, woulde win people from your great multitude of ten Puritanes to one Proteſtant, and from your pleaſant and libertine Religion, to ſo Auſtere, and penitentiall profeſsion, with ſo many diſhonours, as Catholicke worſhip ſhould be in ſuch tearmes. Then Sir you may be ſecured, by all rules of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and reaſon, that Puritaniſme is falſe, and Catholicke Reuerence moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And if the whole ſtate of England it ſelfe, her Maieſtie our ſucceſſor, ſhoulde be moued by ſo many forcible, and vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable true Motyues as this worſhippe hath, yet ſuch common wealth men as you neede not to doubt, but Englande then would be as mighty, and able to defende it ſelfe, againſt Spaine and all forreigners, as England Puritanes would be. Reckon all hundreds of yeares ſince the conqueſt, examine the ſtate of thoſe dayes, before
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17430:43"/>the reuolt of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am deceaued or no. Your ſect hath offended many, but not defended or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted any kingdome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XXI. VNTRVTH.</head>
               <p>BVT howſoeuer obedient and duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Catholickes are, this man procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in his vſuall vaine, and like aſtone deſcending, by how much nearer center, ſo much more violent. And beginneth his Heralds office of defiance, euen to the State it ſelfe, of which he hath bin hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſo kindely carefull. And becauſe he loueth authority and pleadeth for it, of ſuch as be placed therein, and haue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with her Maieſty (he meaneth ſome of her priuie Councell) he affirmeth not only that they haue incurred <hi>Premunire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 38.</note> 
                  <hi>by fauouring, comforting, counſelling, or abetting an appeale to Rome, contrary to the Statute of</hi> 24. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 22. whereby he calleth their liberties, landes, and goodes into queſtion. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he will caſt at all, euen their liues themſelues, chargeth them <hi>not onely with
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17430:43"/>Prieſts and Ieſuites, but to haue receaued ahſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, indulgence, or diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> by ſuch meanes. Which, what an vntruth it is, I neede not vrter; and howe venimous againſt ſuch perſonages, I remit to others cenſure. And concerning the Proteſtant Biſhops, nowe at laſt he rewardeth with <hi>the offalles of the whore of Babilon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 40.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE XXII. AND LAST Vutruth.</head>
               <p>AND as the nature of the ſpirit of theſe pretendors is to rule, &amp; to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, to be at defiance with all, peace with none; ſo nowe he denounceth wars, muſtereth his men, calleth his Lordes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, ſurueyeth his Cities, and Townes,<note place="margin">Pag. 40. 41:</note> numbreth his Gentlemen, Captaines, <hi>men affaction</hi> and <hi>reſolution,</hi> and arrayeth his whole Army in ſuch order &amp; multitudes, ten to one, that if diſſembling, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes may not be admitted, yet his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence is, that he may preuaile by armes. And telleth in plaine tearmes, <hi>that it is not good to prouoke the Puritanes.</hi> And why? for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17430:44"/>becauſe to vſe his wordes. <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and good Townes, Lordes, Gentlemen, and Captaines, (that be of the Religion) incline that way, and be men of action, and reſolution.</hi> And concerning his Chaplaines, thus he boaſteth: <hi>Setting by nonrefidents and dumbe dogges, ye ſhall ſinde ten Puritanes, for one for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt.</hi> What the meaning of theſe men is, requireth no difficulty to decypher. And yet if his wordes were true, I doubt notbut he would diſpute in an other man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (which their ſpirit teacheth) and bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile with weapons &amp; not with words, as they haue threatned in other Pamphlets, and their holy brethren performed in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. But for this time, I will put it in the number of his vntruthes. For if ſo many in authority and credit with her Mareſty, &amp; the Maior part of Parlamet, Clergy, and others are this mans Papiſts, then it cannot be true, that <hi>moſt Lords, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and Captaines, and men of action and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, London, and townes</hi> out of vvhich thoſe Papiſt Burgeſſes were choſen, be for them. And although the affirmation or denyall of them, which ſpeake ſo vntruly, is not to be regarded; yet if we will either
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17430:44"/>conſider their Religion in it ſelfe, what it teacheth, community of thinges, warres, rebellions, ſpoyles, and vſurpation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers labours, fewe will be founde (for I doe not ſpeake but ſome may bee decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) which haue either wit, wealth, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, credit, authority or eſtimation, but woulde bee willing to maintayne them, which in this deſtructine Religion, they cannot performe. Or if we will be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by experience, wee ſhall conſider, that in theſe London and good townes (whereof they glory) onely the meaneſt and moſt needy, which hope by exhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and innouations to be exalted, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their clergy, ſuch as want wealth, and benifices (which they cannot get) enuying at others ſubſtance, haue embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced this Religion. And if they coulde be adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, &amp; change their debaſed eſtate,<note place="margin">Petr. frar. or. cont ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctar. nou. teſt. tr ord. Burg in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat. ſup. edict. Reg. Gal. delenſ. Reg. &amp; Rel.</note> woulde be no more ſcrupulous to change their pretended perfection, then their bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers a Tayler and Cobler at Franckford, which were vnder no lawe before, when they had gotten head conſtituted Lawes, Courts, and Rulers, as their ſpirit taught them. And as <hi>Caluin, Beza, Othoman,</hi> and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17430:45"/>others, both in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> and <hi>Fraunce,</hi> could neither endure riches, or regiment, but kept councels to depoſe Princes and Rulers: yet when themſelues preuayled, could both approoue of riches, and keepe others in ſubiection to their deuiſes.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſe, by theſe ſew things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue exempliſied in ſo ſhorte a Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, how falſely and corruptly hee hath delt, if the reſt of his vntruthes ſhoulde be meaſured with like examine: Which for many cauſes, and not to bee offenſiue, I haue omitted. And therefore, when vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily I paſſe ouer ſo many ſorgeries, let no man thinke, that I haue allowed for truth, ſuch things as I haue not here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuted. And concerning the humilitie, Motyues, loyalty, and loue of this <hi>Aſsoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi> to our gratious Princeſſe, and thoſe Proteſtant Biſhops whome hee taketh in hand to teach, I hope no man will bee ſo moueable to be carried with the motions of him, which not onely without any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue at al, would mooue ſo great a Queene and Kingdome, to go about vtterly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue a Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which had reigned vnre mooued, in her moſt holy and renowmed
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17430:45"/>Anceſtors and this Nation ſo many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeares; and mooued by ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and vnfallible motiues as I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, the whole Chriſtian worlde to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour &amp; defend it: but ſuch as euery man of iudgment (and ſuch as will not be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with euery blaſte of ſuch vnconſtant and contemptible men) may ſuppoſe they were, by which ſo many prowde Pagan Emperours and Princes of the earth, ſo many wiſe and learned Philoſophers, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians, and potent enemies were conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to profeſſe ſo poore and penitentiall life, in regard of thoſe honours and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures they had enioyed. Neither is this the ende and ſcope of that <hi>Aſsociator</hi> as I haue deſcribed: But to mooue our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, firſte to eſtabliſhe that Religion which ſhe hath allowed, onely vntill ſuch time, as he hopeth the former may bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne: And then, both that. and the profeſſors thereof, muſte bee dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and taken away, as his owne wordes haue witneſſed. And that vncertaine, vnconſtant, falſe, and ſeditious profeſsion which neuer hath ende, but euer is in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, contention, diſobedience, rebellion,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17430:46"/>and diſſentions wickedneſſe muſt bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. When the Vicar of <hi>Greenewitch,</hi> or Deane of <hi>Winſor,</hi> or Parſon of any place, where the Queene or King ſhall keepe their Court, may depoſe them as their ſpirit pleaſeth. Which vnder Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritane correction, to vſe this mans phraſe is far more <hi>dangerous to the State in ciuill conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 35:</note> then to maintayne ſupremacie in the See of Rome. And yet I make a doubt, if your <hi>Presbitery</hi> may be planted, and the <hi>pretended perſection</hi> in Religion ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, whether any Queene, King, or Prince, may bee allowed with that ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion. For ſuch Regents are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible of thoſe brethren, vpon vvhome no lawe may be impoſed. Then Nobles, and Councell, are to ceaſe where both community of thinges muſt bee, and ſo many Regalities and Regencies are, as there be Pariſhes in this Nation, thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandes of ſupremacies, more then can giue maintenance to any vnity or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination. As for Proteſtant Biſhops and al ſuch as <hi>depend vpon eccleſiaſtical digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 24.</note> you haue alreade enacted in this Pamphlet, as diſtincte and oppoſite to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17430:46"/>
                  <hi>Puritanes, viz. ſuch as pretend perfection in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi> Howe the depending authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of inferiour Magiſtrates can haue place, where the ſuperiour to which they are ſubordinate, is taken away, it paſſeth my inuention. Or howe the priuate wealth wiues, or any proper of Subiects, can be their peculiers, where euery beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garly, and laſciuious wanton, muſte haue his will, as his ſpiritte leadeth, I finde not in that profeſsion. And yet your owne writinges witneſſe, this vvoulde bee platforme of holy <hi>Aſſotiation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
